Chapter 6 About the Business Value of Expertise

Specialization can transform your marketing, which is awesome, but it can also transform you, and that’s the real reason to get excited about it.

The words skill and expertise are often used interchangeably, but to me they are useful labels for two different but related concepts. Let’s agree, at least for the purposes of the rest of this book, to use skill to describe the technical ability to get something done and expertise to describe understanding business context, planning effectively, and guiding the deployment of skill to that the skill creates desirable business impact. In other words, skill gets it done; expertise ensures it has meaningful impact for your client.

6.1 About skill

Before I go any further, I need to assure you that I deeply respect skill. It has tremendous value to the human race, and it is well worth investing in acquiring skill. Skill is a necessary building block, not an optional one. I am sure that you have worked hard to acquire and refine whatever skill you currently command. So I hope you do not feel insulted when you hear me detail the numerous problems that flow from trying to differentiate yourself from competitors using skill alone. Flour alone is not enough to make a cake, and that fact doesn’t insult the value of flour, so the fact that skill alone is not enough to make your business special does not insult the value of that skill either.

If your business model is based on renting access to your skill alone, then you have a three-pronged problem: 1) Skill markets tend towards commoditization, 2) skills are easily replicated, and 3) differentiating based on skill alone is almost impossible. Let’s understand each of these problems.

6.1.1 Commoditization

I believe modern businesses and human resources departments are what has defined skill as “an ability to perform a discrete, standardized task or group of tasks”. Some specific examples:

Building an API is a different skill than building the front-end code for an app that uses that API.
Coding in Ruby is a different skill than coding in Python.
Using the OpenCV computer vision library is a different skill than building your own low-level computer vision algorithm.
Interviewing users is a different skill than writing code.

From your perspective, your skills are a beautiful tapestry of abilities you have woven together in order to make magic for clients. But from the perspective of an HR person, that beautiful tapestry is a bunch of “Lego blocks” of discrete, modular abilities, and their standardized shape and ability to interlock makes them highly interchangeable. And for better or worse, the way an HR person views skill is pretty much the way all of us who are renting access to skill view it.

This view of skill as a discrete, modular ability makes skill the most easily commoditized aspect of what you do for clients. Commoditization is generally good for the buy side of a market, which gets a choice between many very similar options (what economists refer to as fungible) at a price range that tends to be low. But if a supplier can’t build a “3-legged stool” featuring high quality, high consistency, and low price in their offerings, they won’t thrive in a commoditized market. To be clear, no service supplier really wants to create or participate in a commoditized market for their skills. Instead, commoditized markets emerge when the supply side participants fail or don’t try to create meaningful differentiation between their offerings and the offerings of others in the market. The demand side of a market will generally apply pressure to commoditize it because a commoditized skill market is easier to buy from. In the world of self-employed service providers and freelancers with business models based on skill rather than expertise, this kind of commoditization dynamic is not the exception, it’s the norm.

6.1.2 Easily replicated

Your skills are easily replicated by competitors. The prevalence of open source in the modern custom software development industry and the eagerness of many advanced technologist to share what they know makes it relatively easy to acquire new skill, and the longer a skill has been in existence the more freely available documentation there will be for that skill. The longer a tech platform has been around, the more libraries, frameworks, and best practices will exist to support it and remove the need for advanced skill.

While formal education certainly exists within the world of software development, its importance and usefulness tends to be outweighed by self education. Self educated developers are rarely penalized for a lack of formal education, and there are certainly no formal barriers to entry like the kind of licensing and professional standards bodies that attorneys, accountant, and medical practitioners face. This means that almost anybody can become a professional software developer. This is both good and bad for you, but mostly bad if your only way of claiming you’re better than others is to focus on your skillset.

Becoming a competent software developer requires little money or specialized equipment. It certainly helps a lot to have real world experience, but compare yourself to an attorney or surgeon. If you have the time, you can build all kinds of software that closely approximates commercial software or things clients would hire you to build. Via cloud computing and open source you have access to the exact same tools that Amazon or Netflix run multi-billion dollar businesses on. Now think about someone wanting to become a litigator or surgeon. How can they practice those skills in a situation approximating real life?

6.1.3 Difficult differentiation

Remember in chapter 4 I compared the inherent objective observability of products to the relative lack of observability that services have because services are essentially delivered in secret. Remember in chapter 5 I pointed out the human default to not trust your claims. This means that even if your skills are vastly superior to those of others, it’s difficult for prospective clients to observe, measure, and trust this superiority.

We try to counter this lack of observability by showing the artifacts of our work to clients. We request testimonials and case studies from clients. We get permission to use their logo in our marketing materials. We ask for referrals. We use third-party proof (ex: if the New York Times writes about you, you sure as hell are going to feature that on your website) anywhere we can. In some cases you can point to something publicly available and say “I played a key role in building that”. Except for the last one, these are all post-hoc artifacts of our work, and we hope that they will at least partially address the fact that the actual thing–the actual experience of working with us and the actual deliverable–are usually something only a few people can directly experience. The actual thing is intangible to our prospective clients, and we hope to make it tangible with these artifacts like testimonials, case studies, and so on. But these artifacts only go so far in creating differentiation. They’re important, but by themselves they’re not enough because you have lots of competition with very similar skill and similar artifacts of that skill.

The next attempt at differentiation tends to be process and team. We talk about how we have some kind of great process, and we talk about how amazing our world-class team is. The last resort for differentiation tends to be service: how service-oriented our business is. We talk about how good, flexible, or frequent our communication is. How transparent our project management system is. How technically fluent our account managers are. That kind of thing.

These are valiant attempts at differentiation because they’re talking about how your skill is supported with a robust process and other forms of competence. But that’s exactly the problem: having a good process, team, and ability to provide reasonable customer service are all forms of competence, not forms of excellence and they’re certainly not demonstrating an ability to create outsized value. They’re simply the table stakes you need to buy into the services business game. To be clear, lots of us manage to get into this game without those forms of competence (guilty as charged). That’s why we’re so proud of ourselves when we finally achieve them. We learned them the hard way, on the job. And that is something to be happy about. But to be clear, competence in skill delivery is the minimum, not something that more demanding clients will get excited about. The fact that so many of us are excited about mere competence is actually a sad condemnation of the state of our profession rather than a point of actual pride.

6.1.4 Time-sensitive

In the world of software and technology, skill has a relatively short half-life. To understand why, there are three closely related concepts you need to know about. They are what’s known as the Rogers curve, Ronald Moore’s variation of this idea as described in his book Crossing the Chasm, and Gartner, Inc’s elaboration of the same idea known as the Gartner Hype Cycle.

The Rogers adoption curve comes from a 1962 book by Everett Rogers called Diffusion of Innovations. By dividing us–all of us humans–into 20th percentile groups, the Rogers curve actually describes pretty well how new technology is adopted over time.

{Rogers curve illustration, based on the one from Wikipedia}

The fundamental ideas behind the Rogers curve are change and risk. A very few of us, roughly 2.5%, see an opportunity in the change that new technology presents and have the risk tolerance to eagerly and quickly start using that new tech, despite all the risk of it not working or turning into an expensive, underperforming boondoggle. These are the Innovators at the far left of the Rogers curve. On the far right of the curve are the Laggards–16% of us!–who have the exact opposite relationship to change and risk. Change is seen as a problem, not an opportunity, and they seek to minimize risk as much as possible. This leads Laggards to only reluctantly accept change, and probably with a fair bit of grumbling and risk mitigation efforts along the way. Between Innovators and Laggards lie three more groups, each with a different style for adopting new technology that flows from their relationship particular to change and risk.

Geoffrey Moore evolved this idea in a seemingly small but very significant way.

{Crossing the Chasm illustration}

Moore inserted a “chasm” between the Early Adopters and the Early Majority. This chasm represents the difficulty that new technology ideas and products, especially disruptive ones, have in gaining adoption among the Early Majority. In fact, “crossing the chasm” is so difficult that many new products never make it across.

Although Early Adopters and the Early Majority are depicted as existing right next to each other on the Rogers adoption curve, in reality they are quite different in terms of what they want from new technology. The Early Majority is more pragmatic than the Early Adopters are, and this pragmatism leads them to expect a significantly more robust, reliable product than Early Adopters are willing to accept. This boils down, once again, to risk. The Early Majority is looking for risk mitigation in the form of what Moore calls a “whole product”, meaning the new tech has an ecosystem of support, services, and best practices available to support its successful integration.

Finally, Gartner, Inc. has developed a very useful concept they call the Gartner Hype Cycle, which looks at the Rogers and Moore adoption curves from the perspective of customer expectations relative to the reality of the new idea or product.

{Illustration of Gartner Hype Cycle}

When a technology innovation is brand new, the hyperbole around it is quite high; unrealistically so. The press–especially the segment that uses a click-driven advertising-based revenue model–contributes to this unrealistically high level of hype. The press has discovered, for better or worse, that we want to feel safe by understanding threats. That is a basic human need that the press meets (or exploits) by creating hype around new technologies. Their coverage of new tech answers the following implied questions:

“Who is totally screwed if they don’t know about this new thing soon enough?”
“What implications does this new thing have for our future?”
“Who wins and who loses because of this new thing?”

If you want a very thoughtful, evenhanded answer to questions like those, you’ll pay an analyst or pay to subscribe to a publication like Ben Thompson’s Stratechery. And if you instead donate your clicks and ad views in exchange for answers to those questions, you’ll tend to get overhyped, over-generalized, overstated answers in the form of what most press delivers. This drives the first part of the Gartner Hype Cycle, where the hype far exceeds what’s realistic for this new piece of technology.

That phase doesn’t last forever. At some point–about the time the tech is trying to cross the chasm so the Early Majority can begin integrating it–the hype flips and becomes pessimism. Gartner calls this the Trough of Disillusionment. Again, the part of the press with an ad-based revenue model is eager to help push things further towards an extreme yet again, except this time to a negative extreme. Remember, they are serving a human need to feel safe by knowing about threats.

Except this time, the threat is understood by the press’s answer to these implied questions:

“Who is totally screwed if they made a mistake by jumping on the wrong tech bandwagon?”
“What implications does the shortcomings of this new new thing have for our future?”
“Who wins and who loses if they don’t know about the shortcomings of this new thing?”
“Who can we shame for the shortcomings of this new thing or for mistakenly embracing this new thing when they should have known better?”

Instead of trying to warn you about missing out on the next big thing, the press is warning you about the now-apparent shortcomings of the next possibly big thing. They’re discussing the same technology, but now talking about a different threat it poses. This drives the anti-hype part of the Hype Cycle.

If the technology is able to achieve mainstream adoption, it climbs the Slope of Enlightenment and things stabilize on the Plateau of Productivity. There’s no hype here, just a broadly-accepted, realistic view of what the technology can and cannot do and how it can and cannot create value. The press stops trying to drive positive or negative hype here because the threats this new tech might pose are well-understood, and so those threats are not very useful for driving clicks and ad views, and the tech isn’t really new anymore anyway.

If we superimpose the Hype Cycle over Moore’s variation of the Rogers curve, the relationship between them becomes crystal clear.

{illustration of the above with the Rogers segments labeled across the bottom and the Hype Cycle phases labeled across the top}

Here’s what all this means for a business that focuses on skill alone. There are situations where skill alone makes your services valuable, and you don’t need much of a differentiator. Those situations all lie towards the left end–the head–of these three curves.

{previous illustration updated: Moore/Rogers and Hype Cycle curves are lightened now and a new curve is overlaid. The new curve is the value of skill alone, and it’s highest at the head, stays relatively high across the chasm, and then starts to diminish through early majority, late majority, and then is lowest for the laggards}

Skill alone can make your services valuable when a new technology is very early on in its lifecycle because:

There are few alternatives to your skill simply by virtue of the technology’s youth, so it’s relatively easy for buyers of your services to find you and choose you from among the relatively few alternatives to hiring you. Scarcity drives the value.
Your buyers are comfortable with risk because they are Innovators or Early Adopters.

Those situations where skill alone makes your services valuable are time sensitive. They cluster around new technology, and they don’t last forever. Once that new technology isn’t so new anymore and is supported by a whole product ecosystem of support, services, best practices, frameworks, libraries, and other forms of abstraction and “implementation insurance”, skill alone loses much of its value.

If you’re a typical young software developer, you’re excited by this time-sensitivity because it gives you something to aim your “learning cannon” towards. It delivers periodic “cocaine pellets” of satisfaction as you conquer a series of learning curves, and when the skill is no longer scarce and valuable, you’re fine with moving on to the next hot new thing.

If you think of yourself more as a business owner, this time-sensitive quality is somewhere between a neutral fact of life at best, a nuisance, or significant risk at worse. And if you’re focused on using expertise as the raw material to build an awesome career that last 20 years or more, you’ll do everything you can to wrap time-sensitive skill in evergreen expertise.

6.1.5 Easily replaceable

Focusing on skill alone makes your business easily replaceable. Remember that skills tend to be defined as discrete blocks of ability. This modularity makes it easier for the business to build a human-powered system, but those human building blocks are meant to be like the interchangeable parts that were such a huge part of the industrial revolution. If all you have to offer is skill–especially one that is a more mature skill–you will make your business easily replaceable.

6.1.6 Own vs. rent

If your skill is strategically important to a company, that company will prefer to “own” rather than “rent” it. Owning the skill means hiring a full time employee or building out an internal capability to deliver that skill rather than renting it, which means working with outside contractors, freelancers, or consultants. I don’t think you can make a convincing case that owning a strategically-important skill actually produces superior results to renting it, but that doesn’t stop companies from acting as if it does.

Startups are one place where you can see this very clearly. Digital product startups do work with outside contractors, freelancers, or consultants, but they’d always prefer own strategically important skills because of how this effects company valuation during funding or acquisition rounds. They’re incentivized to own rather than rent skill by incentives that have little to do with actual company performance.

Again, none of the above is meant to denigrate the value of skill. I simply want you to understand the limited ability of skill alone to make your business valuable. Skill alone is quickly commoditized, easily replicated, and does little to make your company uniquely different from competitors. If your attempt at differentiation is to claim “My company will meet spec and deliver this project on or under budget”, then you are absolutely setting yourself up to play the commoditization game. You are inviting clients to think of you as a commodity.

6.2 About impact

I often say: skill gets it done; expertise creates impact. If skill gets it done and expertise creates impact, what is impact?

There are multiple ways you can think of impact, including:

Improving your client’s condition. This is Alan Weiss’ way of describing the goal of consulting, and it’s a good, broad way to think about impact.
Creating an observable–possibly measurable–change for your client. Often referred to as “moving the needle” for your client.
Reducing the risk of change, either a change the company has initiated (integrating new technology, for example), or risk from the outside the company is reacting to (complying with new government regulations, for example).
Helping a client create new opportunities, like entering a new market, for example.
Changing the broader culture of an industry or type of company. This is a change that’s bigger than any one business, and is often done from a position of thought leadership. As an example, you might think of how test-driven development has become a popular working method due to the work of multiple thought leaders repeatedly making a case for the value of this approach. Their thought leadership has been impactful in the world of software development.

Skill, and an ability to work with clients to create impact, are relevant at all points on the Rogers curve, but their roles and relative value change as you traverse the curve.

{TODO: consider superimposing several lines on the hype cycle, including perceived risk of deploying the skill, something about commoditization, etc.}

At the head of the hype cycle, skill alone is often enough because nobody really has real expertise deploying that skill, unless you have expertise with some adjacent skill (ex: your expertise with previous generation wireless sensors positions you well to gain skill with IoT and add value with IoT projects). Additionally, at this early date you are selling to innovators and early adopters, who have an entirely different relationship to risk than the rest of the groups on the Rogers curve. They’re perspective is more like “Let’s see what this can do!” rather than “who do we blame/sue if things go wrong?”.

As you enter the middle of the hype cycle, skill starts to become commoditized and expertise becomes relatively more important because you’re dealing with a much less risk-averse and much more demanding group of buyers: the Early and Late Majorities.

As you enter the rightmost region of the hype cycle, skill becomes very commoditized and expertise remains important but gains a competing and much cheaper alternative: best practices, libraries, toolkits, and frameworks. At this phase, risk generally declines, except for edge cases. Expertise still plays a role because despite its maturity, technology is complex and easily screwed up, even when supported with a full ecosystem of support, best practices, a mature services ecosystem, and other forms of risk mitigation.

Let’s pull a few representative examples to build a timeline of how much time tends to pass before a given tech platform becomes mostly commoditized.

TODO: timeline constructed based on mobile, and a few others.

6.3 About expertise

If skill gets it done and expertise creates impact, what actually is expertise?

There are multiple ways you can think of expertise, including:

Expertise guides the deployment of skill. Skill knows how to do it, expertise decides what to do and knows why to do it.
Expertise guides, informs, or improves decision-making. It reduces uncertainty in decision-making, or offers a methodology to reduce uncertainty.
Expertise improves business outcomes in ways that skill alone cannot because expertise incorporates more context than skill does. Expertise can be a force-multiplier for skill.
Expertise helps you predict and manage the second-order consequences of applied skill or other causes of change.
The output of applied expertise is business impact; the output of abstracted expertise is best practices or other intellectual property (IP). IP in the world of services is expertise made usable by non-experts.

It often seems to me that expertise–if we can think of it as an elemental force of nature–seeks venn diagram overlaps between impact and risk in the world of business. Like water seeks to run downhill, expertise seems to seek out this particular combination of heightened impact and heightened risk. Experts feel a sort of gravitational pull towards this overlap between impact and risk, and that’s how they choose where to deploy their curiosity and energy. I suppose you could also explain things through survivorship bias. It’s possible that experts just “follow their muse” and the market rewards those that focus on the impact/risk overlap with more successful businesses. Either way, there’s a strong relationship between expertise and this risk/impact overlap in the world of business.

The differences between expertise and skill make it possible to build two different kinds of businesses. They’re both considered services businesses, but that’s where the similarities end. I refer to a business where skill is the primary asset as an output-based business. And one where expertise is the primary asset is an expertise-based business.

6.3.1 The output-based business model

In an output-based business model, you’re most likely promising outputs that are measured in the following ways:

How well does it meet spec?
How much did it cost to build (measured solely in units of time)?
You might measure bugs, reliability, or other forms of functionality.
You might measure quality as well.

At the advanced level of this business model, you’re promising outputs that are measured differently:

What potential value could this create for your client, and what actual value did it create after it was deployed?
ROI on the cost of building, where it’s assumed that both client and service provider should get positive ROI from the project. Could be thought of as “profit sharing” in that the service provider realizes a good profit on the work and the work produces a good ROI for the client.

Implementation tends to play a critical role in the output-based business model. Providing advice and helping your client make better decisions will be an inevitable part of the output-based business, but these elements are secondary to how this kind of business works.

6.3.2 The expertise-based business model

With an expertise-based business model, you’re most likely promising things measured in the following ways:

Impact or transformation
Moving a revenue or cost needle
Risk mitigation
Gains in competitive advantage

If you can deliver on these promises then it is almost certainly because you are bringing a combination of expertise and implementation capacity to the table, but you are leading projects with the expertise. This changes almost everything about your business:

You are more likely to interact directly with client-side people who can commission and fund projects without having to check with their boss.
You are more likely to be involved upstream in the project and have influence over key decisions about architecture, design, and other critical upstream choices.
You are more likely to be able to charge for your advice alone, or to frame having access to you as a valuable form of insurance that ensures the project goes well.
You can create and monetize intellectual property (IP), which is your expertise packaged in a way that makes it usable by non-experts.
You are more likely to push back against client assumptions or decisions. You lead in the project more than you follow.
Your sales conversations with clients change. You still discuss scope and specifications, but you probably spend more time asking simple questions about motivation and context. You spend more time helping your client explore other possibilities and less time assuming that their a priori assumptions and decisions are valid. And overall, you’re more willing to walk away from a potential sale where the client won’t let you lead.

6.4 Expertise and marketing

I often say: expertise is both the cause and effect of good marketing. This paradox is at the heart of how you rapidly cultivate self-made expertise.

If you’re willing to do something quite simple that seems incredibly risky but actually is not very risky at all, you can use your marketing itself to accelerate your cultivation of valuable expertise. This is what people in my Expertise Incubator program do, so I’ll outline the structure of that program as a way to get you thinking about how your marketing can feed forward into your cultivation of expertise.

6.4.1 Marketing as an expertise accelerant

If you’re following my framework, you don’t wait until you’ve cultivated this deep, valuable expertise to share it. You share it as you go.

This part is CRITICAL.

You share. it. as. you. go.

This does two things.

First, it helps you more quickly develop the reputation you’re trying to develop. We humans are amazing at ignoring things we deem irrelevant, but repetition–showing up over and over again in a consistent way–helps defeat this human default of “ignore everything we can”. It helps you earn attention.

Second, it accelerates your cultivation of deep expertise.

Ponder this image for a moment, because this is basically what I’m suggesting you do to accelerate your cultivation of expertise:

TODO: 36th chamber image

That’s a scene from The 36th Chamber of Shaolin. A student is training by carrying heavy buckets of water and those little sword things attached to his arms will poke or stab him in the side if he drops his arms too much.

Bear with me here, because this is going to sound a little crazy. I am in fact suggesting that you do the following three things:

Build a small audience you can share with. Make sure it’s on a platform with a good feedback mechanism, like an email list.
Share with them on an aggressive schedule; at least 3 times/week. Intentionally work in public at the edge of your expertise. Use their questions and feedback to direct how you deepen your expertise.
Intentionally use the fear created by #2 above to speed up how quickly you cultivate expertise.

When you share your somewhat embryonic expertise with an audience that can give you feedback, you are doing something that will create productive discomfort. This will incentivize you to get better fast.

The stakes are high, but lower than promising a client expertise that you haven’t yet cultivated. In other words, you’re leaning out over your skis, but not on a client project. Doing that on a client project would be a kind of malpractice, and that’s not what I’m suggesting here.

Instead, I’m suggesting you build a small audience (a few hundred or thousand people on an email list will do) and publish to your list frequently about your area of expertise.

At first you’ll basically feel like a fraud.

Over time, the questions & feedback you get from your list, and your own fear of being so close to the edge of your expertise will force rapid improvement. If you’re in the “epidermis of expertise”, you’ll quickly move to the dermis.

At the same time as you’re cultivating deeper expertise, you’ll also be building a reputation–aka a market position–as the go-to person for whatever it is you’re talking about 3 or more days a week to your list. The self-critical part of you is saying right now that this can’t happen, but I’m here to tell you that part of you is wrong. I’ve seen it happen too many times to believe your inner critic over my own experience. :)

Your inner critic is saying “nobody would trust or work with an expert who doesn’t have 30 years of experience and doesn’t have all the answers.” And again, your inner critic is wrong.

This is my solution to the “chicken and egg problem” of becoming a self-made expert.

It’s not easy, and it’s not emotionally comfortable, but it is something I’ve tested and can tell you works, and it’s faster than other methods (formal education, for example).

6.4.2 Expertise as a marketing accelerant

Which of this pair of content would you rather put behind an opt-in gate?

The 5 things you must know to get your development environment set up
How your startup can gain a competitive advantage by knowing when to use and when not to use micro services

It’s probably obvious: the first one comes from skill, the second from expertise (if they live up to the promise embedded in their respective titles).

Which of the two following talks do you think would be more likely to attract someone who can cut a check for your services?

TODO

Which of the two following emails to an email list do you think would be more likely to get a response from list members:

Tabs vs. spaces
The business impact of blockchain

OK, that was a trick question. We all know the tabs vs. spaces one would get at least some replies because it’s a polarizing topic, even though it has very little to do with expertise or business impact. Let’s try again :)

Why well-documented code matters
The business impact of blockchain

Also kind of a trick question! It really depends who is on your list, doesn’t it? But that gets to an important point. If your list was mostly topics like the first one, it’s likely your list will mostly be made up of your peers. A list that frequently discusses topics like the second one is much more likely to attract folks who desire insight on the business impact of {things}, and those folks–surprise surprise–tend to be able to also spend money to achieve business impact.

I hope these examples have made my point for me. That point being: demonstrating real expertise in your marketing attracts folks who need that expertise, and those folks also tend to seek business impact and be reasonably well-supplied with money to aid their quest for business impact. Demonstrating real expertise in your marketing helps you connect and build trust with buyers for your services.

6.5 Chapter Summary

Parking Lot

Profit is a lagging indicator of impact

Modeling expertise

TODO: the 3-layer skin model for expertise

Chapter 4 Positioning vs. Specialization

When I ask you to think of the best cloud platform as a service, what company or platform do you think of?

No matter whether you thought of AWS, GCP, Digital Ocean, or one of dozens of other cloud providers, you are responding to that product or company’s reputation. That reputation may be private to you, or it may be shared among a group of people. Here’s what I mean.

There’s a product called Zencastr that records podcasts interviews using a browser-based, double-ended approach. Zencastr has a generally positive reputation among the group of podcasters that I am friends with, but I have a very negative view of Zencastr. The product’s “private” reputation with me as an individual is in tatters because the product failed me the two times I tried it. That’s a 100% failure rate! Others have had different experiences with a more favorable success rate.

It’s no surprise that I personally dislike Zencastr and avoid using it while others who are demographically similar to me like it and prefer to use it. The product’s reputation as it exists inside my mind is not good, while its reputation as it exists inside the mind of my peer group is very different, and much more positive. Same product, multiple reputations.

A reputation that is similar across a group of people is also known as a market position.

Shall we play a game?

Either physically or mentally, make a dot on the diagram below. Where you place the dot should accurately describe your perception of two product lines. One dot for Apple’s products, and another dot for Facebook’s products.

{TODO:Blank 2x2 matrix with cost on one axis and security on the other}

Show and tell time. How much does your diagram look like mine?

{TODO:My filled-in 2x2}

Just notice how similar or different your placement of Apple and Facebook’s dots are to mine. It’s not that mine are “right” and yours are or aren’t “right”. That’s not the point here at all, because there is no right or wrong placement of dots. Instead, the dots tell us something about Apple and Facebook’s reputations as they exist inside my mind and your mind.

Let’s revisit the Zencaster example. Here’s a similar 2x2 matrix showing Zencastr’s reputation as it exists in my mind compares to how it exists in the minds of my podcaster friends:

{TODO: 2x2 with value of features on one axis and reliability on the other, with a cluster of dots from my peers in the high value, reasonably reliable quadrant and my lone dot on the high value, low reliability quadrant}

Generally, the more consistency there is in the placement–or positioning–of Apple, Facebook, Zencastr, or any business on a diagram like this, the more widely shared and homogenous that companies reputation–or market position–is.

There’s a seeming contradiction in this idea of a market position. If we could survey every living human, we would probably find very few businesses with a highly homogenous market position. If we could ask every living human to place Apple and Facebook on our 2x2 matrix, we’d find lots of variances because people have a wide range of preferences and worldview filters. If different people place–or position–the same product or company in different positions on this matrix, how can any company have a clearly defined market position? Said differently, how can any company know how its products or services are perceived by the market?

In practice, this is not actually a problem, and it’s especially un-problematic for you because most companies and definitely yours will never need to be perceived in precisely the same way by every human on the planet. Most small services businesses can get away with the right group of 1,000 to 10,000 people perceiving them the “right” way. Helping that many people perceive you the way you want to be perceived is still no small feat, but it’s infinitely more achievable than trying to help every human on the planet perceive you the way you want to be perceived.

A market position–again, your reputation–is how you are perceived by the group of people who need to know about you for your business to thrive.

This “group of people who need to know about you for your business to thrive” thing is important. We marketers have a shorthand for this: your target market.

Lots of us who start out as freelancers and then graduate to consultants or entrepreneurs or agency owners start out with an accidental target market. We don’t choose it; we inherit it, and usually we take whatever we can get. Additionally, these initial target markets are a haphazard and heterogenous mixture of our personal network, past clients, friends, and random business associates. They look like a Jackson Pollock painting.

Then, we become more intentional and willing to be more disciplined, and that means either sticking with a subset of our initial target market because we have a head start there, or intentionally choosing a different target market because our interest doesn’t align with a head start or because we have no head start at all.

Target market selection is at first very much about finding the right “home” for your skills then later staying committed to a place where you can cultivate valuable expertise. A supply of water has relatively high value in the desert and relatively lower value in a rain forest. In other words, value is contextual. If you find yourself in a rain forest with a supply of water you want to sell, you can either move to a desert (new target market) or find something else to sell (change your skills, expertise, or packaging of those things). Creating exceptional value is very much about identifying the right context within which to create that value.

Let’s review: Your market position is your reputation among a specific group of people. This means you need to make some decisions:

How do you want to be perceived?
Among what group do you want to be perceived that way?
You probably are not currently perceived in the way you’d like to be. So the last question is: what needs to happen now to create the reputation you want later?

 The decision you make now in service of a future reputation is usually some form of specialization.

If you’re reading closely, you’ll have noticed that I used the word positioning in the title of this book and in some of the previous chapters, but I have not used it in this chapter until now. That’s because, strictly speaking, the word “positioning” is a verb. It’s a thing you do.

Except when it comes to marketing, that’s exactly what it is not. A position–or more specifically a market position–is not a verb. It is more like a noun. It is a thing that exists in the minds of a group of people. It’s a concept, an association, a feeling, or a vivid memory. Those are all nouns, not verbs. Things, not actions.

So why is it so commonly said “Company X is positioning itself as {thing}” or, “You need to position your business”? I’ll dive more into this in the next chapter, but for now just know that people mean one of two things when they say “positioning”, and you have to dig a little deeper to know which of those two things they mean.

For now, just know that it’s a sort of lazy convention within marketing to talk about the process of building a desirable market position (reputation) as “positioning”. Even I make this mistake from time to time, despite striving to be accurate in how I speak.

That said, there is a verb that describes exactly what it is you do to build a desirable market position. That verb is “specialize” or “specialization”.

4.1 Specializing is an action

The act of specializing is based on a decision about focus. Where do you want to focus? You could focus on a target market, focus on type of problem you want to solve, focus on a type of change you want to effect, or focus on a specific and possibly unique way of delivering your services. There really are only about 4 different ways you can focus.

After you’ve made the decision about where to focus (there will be much more about making this decision this later in this book), you apply time and discipline to grow this seed of a decision into a desirable market position. I like this analogy: The decision about how exactly to specialize is the seed, time and discipline are the nourishment that seed needs, and the plant we see growing out of the ground after some time passes is the market position.

{TODO: book cover/theme image shown here}

4.2 About time

Time is a critical element in cultivating a market position for a services business. You can’t create the market position overnight, just like no plant grows from a seed to maturity overnight. The concept of a market position applies to more than just services, it also applies to products and brands. When we look at how services businesses and product businesses cultivate a market position, we see some significant differences, especially as it relates to time. Understanding these differences will help you contextualize the various bits of advice about positioning that you’ll come across from various sources.

Product positioning is based on the inherent objective observability of a product, and the ability of advertising to amplify a message about those observable features.

The superior build quality of Apple’s first generation unibody aluminum MacBooks was easily observable when compared to Windows PCs of the same generation. Almost anybody paying any level of attention would notice the sturdy yet smooth movement of the hinge that supported the MacBook screen. That person could pick up the computer and try to flex or twist it and see how strong it was. They could bang on the keyboard and feel how little give there was. And side by side with a same-generation Windows PC, they would notice a distinct difference in build quality.

This is what I mean when I say products have an inherent objective observability. You can see, feel, smell, taste, and measure the differences between products. This lends a sense of objectivity to how we compare products. Products also tend to have fixed, known prices, which further lends a sense of objectivity to how we compare them. “Apple is expensive, but very high quality. PCs are cheaper but lower quality.” Reasonable people can disagree on those bottom line assessments, but at least you can explain why you arrive at that conclusion. “See! When you press on the MacBook’s case it doesn’t flex at all! When you press on this PC’s case, it flexes 2 or 3 millimeters. That’s why the Apple is more expensive!”

Services have no such objective observability.

Because most services are custom scope, custom price, and delivered under various forms of secrecy, they lack this quality of objective observability. We try to compensate for this with case studies, testimonials, and other post hoc artifacts that come from successful engagements. This is how we try to make our services seem more objectively observable, but ultimately they are not. They’re like any human relationship: there’s the reality of the relationship, there’s what your close friends know about it, and there’s what everybody else thinks they know about it. Those are three distinctly different categories of knowledge about the actual thing.

The inherent observability of products means that advertising or PR can be used to amplify that observability and more quickly build a market position. Even if you’ve never driven a car made by Tesla Motors, you probably know roughly what it would be like to drive one. That’s because you’ve seen them photographed, videoed, talked about, reacted to by others–all at scale–and this creates for you a mental model of what it would be like to drive the car.

Contrast your mental model of what it would be like to drive a Tesla with your mental model of what it would be like to hire and work with McKinsey & Company. That’s also a prestigious brand, but it’s a services company with much less inherent observability. If you’ve never hired or worked with McKinsey & Company, how would you possibly know what it’s like to have the experience of working with them?

The inherent observability of products means it can be faster and easier to develop a reputation for a product. With a $5,000 budget and a week of time you could develop a reputation for a product that doesn’t even exist. I’m not saying this is legal or ethical, but it would work. You mock up a product, Photoshop it into Facebook ad creative associating it with someone currently famous within the culture you’re focused on (this is the unethical/illegal part because it implies this famous person’s endorsement which they haven’t actually given you), target the ad effectively, and you’ve have a pretty good shot for developing a reputation quickly–or at least a “micro-reputation”. In doing this you would be tapping into latent associations, beliefs, and stories in order to more quickly build a reputation for your imaginary product. Some who see the add will react like this:”Kim Kardashian is such an annoying person. I’d never buy something she recommends.” Others will react like this: “Kim Kardashian is amazing. She made herself into a celebrity with nothing but hustle and smarts. I love buying the products she recommends.” Two stories; two different ways your fast-track product reputation-building could go.

To be fair, some of this also applies at least partially to the world of services. There are “hacks” that can more quickly build your reputation–at least among individuals. Price, visual branding, and certain forms of social proof are three of these “hacks” because they’re signals that shortcut some of the normal work or time required for reputation-building.

In the main, however, a reputation for a services business takes time to build. It’s something like a seed for a tree, which will take years to grow into something substantial. Reputations are built over years, not days or weeks (though I scarcely need mention they can be damaged much faster than they can be built). You should plan on 2 to 3 years of focused, disciplined effort to translate a specialization decision into a strong market reputation.

4.3 Standing on shoulders

I did not invent the concepts of market position and specializing. Far from it! These concepts were formalized decades ago, and have been around in some less well defined form for centuries. Others {TODO: footnote them} have written very useful books that are well worth reading if you’re a student of marketing or wanting to understand a variety of perspectives on positioning.

I wrote this book because nobody else has explained exactly how specialization, market position, and expertise relate to each other within the domain of solo practitioners or small shops who provide technology consulting services. Taking advantage of these three concepts can transform your business, and so a book that addresses them within the specific context of a business like yours needed to exist.

4.4 Chapter Summary

TODO

Chapter 11 Risk

You probably mis-perceive the risk levels of various activities. Let’s look at one manifestation of risk: accidental death. Specifically, the lifetime odds of dying from various causes.

Which one seems like a more likely cause of death for most people? Unintentional drug poisoning or car crash? How about dying in a fire (literally) vs. dying in a plane crash? I’d bet you guessed wrong on both of those. I would have too if I didn’t have these actual numbers from the Insurance Information Institute:

Accidental drug poisoning: 1 in 70 lifetime odds of dying this way
Motor vehicle accident: 1 in 102 lifetime odds of dying this way
Exposure to smoke, fire and flames: 1 in 1,506 lifetime odds of dying this way
Air and space transport accidents: 1 in 10,101 lifetime odds of dying this way

–Source: https://www.iii.org/fact-statistic/facts-statistics-mortality-risk

So, you’re more likely to die of accidental drug poisoning than in a car crash, and more likely to die in a fire than in a plane crash! I would have guessed the oppose on each one of those pairs. To me, this points to one simple takeaway: we tend to misunderstand risk! This is because we over-weight factors that aren’t correlated with risk (car crashes look gruesome while drugs look like clean- small pills or pure liquids), under-weight factors that are, and suffer from all sorts of cognitive biases that interfere with our ability to accurately assess risk (the availability heuristic is one biggie). Let’s try to clarify the topic of risk with some important supporting ideas and a self-administered risk assessment that’s a simplified version of what I use with my clients.

I am not a psychologist. I don’t even play one on TV. That said, it’s useful to think about two ideas that attempt to generalize a basket of personality characteristics and motivations into “types”. As with all generalizations, 100% fidelity to individual cases is impossible, so take this with a grain of salt.

11.1 Missionary - Mercenary spectrum

One useful idea is that we all fall somewhere on a spectrum with “missionaries” on one end and “mercenaries” on the other.

Missionaries are motivated by a sense of purpose that’s not fundamentally money-making in nature. Missionaries certainly may find a way to get paid–and perhaps quite well–for pursing their purpose, but that’s not what drives them. It might be a desire to change the culture (or some small aspect thereof), it might be a desire to improve things in some specific or far-reaching way, or it might be a desire to build something new they just feel driven to build.

This raises the question: if you’re a missionary, do you invent your mission or does it find you? What I’ve seen is that they’re both common, and neither is inherently superior or more effective.

Mercenaries are in it for the money. This blunt description might seem like a dismissal but it’s not. It’s just that mercenaries are simple to describe. :)

Now obviously, even if human behavior was simple enough to describe with this missionary-mercenary generalization (it’s not), we’d still find elements of both types in every person. Even missionaries are going to act like mercenaries at times when they need the money more than they need the satisfaction of living out their mission. And even mercenaries will seek the meaning and satisfaction of some kind of mission, even if that mission is chosen and optimized to maximize its potential monetary upside.

That said, when I ask coaching clients to place themselves somewhere on this missionary-mercenary spectrum, almost everybody has an easy time doing so. So there’s something true and resonant about how this idea generalizes our motivations into a simple duality.

How do these two types respond to risk? I haven’t found any significant difference in how they respond to risk, however I believe there is a difference in how they respond to complex, long-term projects where there are many opportunities to make mistakes, recover from mistakes, or not recover from mistakes. I believe the missionaries do better with these kinds of projects. In other words, I believe missionaries do better with risky, lengthy projects because they have something other than financial payoff motivating them. Missionaries tend to have an ability to envision a medium or long-term future where their mission has created significant value, and the vision of that future value keeps them motivated through the lengthy journey it may take to get there. It would be tempting to say that mercenaries should avoid these kinds of projects, but that would be exactly the kind of over-generalization I want to avoid.

11.2 Entrepreneur - Craftspeople spectrum

There’s another way to generalize human motivation that’s a bit more specific to creative professionals (which includes developers). It’s another over-simplified spectrum.

On one end are the entrepreneurs. There are lots of definitions of entrepreneur, but for services businesses I prefer to think of an entrepreneur as one who decouples their income from the time they spend working on client deliverables. You can do this in a variety of ways, not all of which require building a team where you leverage other people’s time. There are plenty of entrepreneurial businesses with one person doing all the value creation and delivery, but in a way where much of that value creation is de-coupled from their time.

On the other end of this spectrum are the craftspeople. They love their craft above almost everything else. They might be heard saying “if only I could spend all my time on my craft…”. Or alternately, when asked what’s special about their business, their response centers almost completely on their abilities as a craftsperson.

It’s tempting to elevate one of these types above the other, but that would be completely unfair and arbitrary. It takes both types for modern society to function and thrive. Both types can make excellent business owners. Both types can become successful specialists who build wonderful market positions. And neither type is more likely to have a better or more satisfying career.

Now that said, entrepreneur types will usually be more flexible about how they structure their business, while craftspeople will likely be less flexible. Entrepreneurs will be less constrained by the realities of the market, while craftspeople will sometimes be more constrained by those realities. This has real implications for how you choose to specialize.

If you’re on the Craftsperson end of this spectrum, you face two constraints, and certain combinations of those constraints can present a very difficult obstacle to successfully specializing.

Let’s start exploring this using this diagram, which I often use as a one-picture explanation of how specialization works.

The entrepreneur has a very large Stuff They Can Do circle, because they tend to be aware of how easily acquired skill is (either through renting the skill or learning it at a competent level just-in-time), so they’ll tend to start with the Stuff Clients Need circle, figure out what clients value and is rare on the supply side of the market and gravitate there. Thus, they’ll define Stuff They Can Do based on Stuff Clients Will Pay Top Dollar For. They’ll start on the left side of that diagram and move to the right in order to build a business model.

The craftsperson approaches things from right to left on this diagram. They tend to assume that Stuff They Can Do is fixed and difficult to change, and the Stuff They Can Do is constrained by their current skill as a developer, designer, artist, writer, etc. They can easily imagine increasing that skill (going deeper into it or expanding it), but they can less easily imagine building up an entirely different skill, especially one that has been dictated by marketplace demand.

This is so partly because for many craftspeople, their skill is part of their identity as a person. It’s part of how they see themselves as someone who is a contributing member of society.

So this is the first constraint craftspeople face. They’re relatively attached to their current definition of Stuff They Can Do, and changing it can feel like a crisis of identity, or a major reinvention of self.

The second constraint is the market (this is the Stuff Clients Need circle on my diagram). You have even less control over what the market wants. In fact, it’s healthiest to simply believe that you have zero control over what the market wants. While it’s not 100% true, acting as if you have no control at all over what the market wants makes you a better small business owner. So yeah, let’s go with that. You have zero control over what the market wants, and that’s just the way things are. All you can do is understand what the market currently wants or try to predict what it will want soon or predict what it wants, doesn’t know it wants, but would definitely want If you invented it for them.

There definitely are situations where for a given person, there is no overlap at all between the Stuff Clients Need and the Stuff You Can do circles. In this situation, if you’re completely inflexible about changing the size, shape, or position of the Stuff You Can Do circle, what you have is a standoff–an irresolvable conflict–and I can’t imagine building a successful business under those conditions.

For the craftspeople reading this, I want to soften the above with a few really interesting examples of craftspeople who would seem to be in that standoff situation but have made it work.

Ross MacDonald specializes in making paper movie props. The copy of A Farewell to Arms that Bradley Cooper’s character in A Silver Linings Playbook throws through the window? Ross MacDonald made that prop. The Pawnee Charter that appears at various places in Parks & Rec? MacDonald made that too, in addition to thousands of other paper movie props. This guy’s an amazing craftsperson, and he’s made specialization work for him.

Sean McCabe started his business with a surprisingly successful course on hand lettering. I don’t know the guy at all, but he sure looks from the outside like an entrepreneurial craftsperson, because he’s cultivated significant skill in multiple crafts (hand lettering, podcasting, writing, internet marketing) and turned each of those into courses that he sells and apparently makes good money selling.

The takeaway is this: there are weird and wonderful examples of craftspeople who have made a business out of their weird and specific skill. And maybe that could be you! But do be warned that your dedication to your craft can be both an asset in some specialization scenarios or it can be a liability that prevents you from specializing at all.

Finally, it’s worth noting that this analogy breaks down totally if you think of entrepreneurs whose craft is the business they are building. This dissolves any difference between these two types. The analogy is still valuable, this edge case notwithstanding.

Bringing this all back to risk: if you are pretty far towards the pure craftsperson end of the spectrum, you will perceive the entrepreneurial aspects of self-employment as relatively risky because they threaten your identity. For example, a “pure entrepreneur” would likely see all of the following as opportunities they could take advantage of. In fact, each of the changes I’ll list below are a key part of a real, successful business model, an example of which I’ve indicated in parentheses:

The commoditization of WordPress skill (WPCurve)
The commoditization of design skill (99designs)
The commoditization of writing skill (AudienceOps)
The absolute glut of people wanting to build a digital startup and the glut of overseas software development talent that’s qualified to help (Rootstrap has productized the early stages of digital product design—from concept to wireframes+pitch deck—and leverages an offshore team to profitable offer development services)
The rise of tools like Squarespace that commoditize web design (Knapsack Creative and Worstofall Design use these tools to deliver “website/brand in a day” services)

For each of these changes in the marketplace there are craftspeople who actually suffer real financial damage, and there are entrepreneurs who leverage the exact same change into a great business. The different outcome is more a result of mindset than anything else. As I like to say: everything is an opportunity.

I want this book to provide a useful, detailed, nuanced framework that helps you specialize and cultivate a great market position for your business, so I tend to avoid broad, absolute declarations. That said, if you are a pure craftsperson and feel inflexibly attached to that identity, your specialization options will be limited, and you may be better off pursuing other ways of improving your business. Partially productizing your craft is one such option.

11.3 Risk tolerance vs. risk profile

A brief sidebar on expertise. I often say this about expertise:  Specialization is a voluntary narrowing that is in service of a future wider impact. You subtract until your focus is narrow enough to penetrate into the hypodermis of a mystery, then you recruit the needed resources from any corner of the world to unravel that mystery and synthesize an effective solution.

This is exactly what’s happened with my very narrow (very “meta”) focus on specialization. At the superficial layer of expertise (what I call the “epidermis of expertise”), my thinking was “Specialize, stupid! Just do it! It’s great for everybody!”. I remained narrowly focused and reached the next layer of the problem: the “dermis of expertise”. The problem become more complex, and required a more nuanced solution. Actually, the problem was always more complex, it’s just that I didn’t realize this until I got past the epidermis of expertise.

The dermis of expertise is where you maintain the narrow focus, but you start casting your eyes towards the horizon, seeking additional helpful resources, be they skill, adjacent or non-adjacent expertise, or anything else that helps you solve the problem. And as you continue on to the deepest later of the problem (the “hypodermis of expertise”), you start to recruit these other resources and incorporate them into your solution.

This is how experts transform an initial narrow focus into a complete solution to a difficult, complex problem. It’s very much like a hypodermic needle. It’s narrow and sharp to allow it to easily penetrate deep, but once deep in the skin it releases its contents which diffuse broadly into the surrounding tissue.

Again, this models how I became interested in risk, risk tolerance, and risk profile. I initially focused on how self-employed software developers can use specialization to their benefit, but ended up needing to learn about risk tolerance (to name just one non-adjacent area of expertise), and the best place I found for doing that–aside from some academic research on prospect theory–was the world of professional wealth management. Does this make me a non-specialist? Not at all! This is how specialization works. You go narrow so that you have more than a snowball’s chance in hell of getting past the epidermis layer of the problem, and once you are past that layer you eagerly go broad in terms of how you solve the problem.

This is why I see the “specialist vs. polymath” debate as a waste of time. It takes a rare special case (the truly successful polymath) and compares it against another rare special case (the irrelevant specialist). Both cases are edge cases that don’t help much in terms of suggesting best practices that apply to more common cases. In other words, it’s rare for a specialist to find an interesting, complex problem that lies at the dermis or hypodermis of expertise and resist going broad in search of a complete solution. Bonified polymaths have told me that they see themselves more as serial specialists. Anyway!

It’s easy to think of risk solely in terms of risk tolerance. But the investment advice/wealth management world has a more nuanced take on risk, and this is beneficial to us here.

The key insight from the investment advice/wealth management world is to distinguish between someone’s emotional and intellectual response to risk, and their ability to withstand a financial loss.

This actually gives us three ways to look at your relationship to risk:

Risk tolerance: your emotional and intellectual response to risk.
Risk capacity: your ability to withstand a financial loss.
Risk profile: A synthesis of the above two, which defines your relationship to risk. This is the single most useful of these three ways of looking at risk.

So to work out a client’s risk profile, I have developed a survey that explores the following areas:

1) Your self-reported comfort with risk. This is a useful “bullshit detector” when compared against more accurate indicators like behavior, so I’m always interested in seeing what kind of delta might exist between self-reported risk tolerance and measured risk tolerance. Note that my measurement is imperfect, but it’s informative. TODO: data on this.

2) Your past behavior with financial risk-taking. What we say and what we do are often quite different, and behavior is a more accurate signal of risk tolerance. There are other forms of risk-taking, like risking social status by doing something your social circle doesn’t accept or understand. But those are not easy to quantify, so I’ve stuck with what is easier to quantify and represents real risk-taking for most folks: spending money now under conditions of uncertainty about how that money might deliver a return on investment in the future and whether it might deliver a return at all.

3) The length of your “runway”, defined as how long your business could survive without landing any new clients starting today, measured in months. This is not the only way to measure risk capacity, but it’s a pretty good one. There are other forms of financial resilience beyond a savings account, but again those are less easy to quantify than “months of burn in a savings account, line of credit, or both“.

4) Your response to prospect theory questions. Wikipedia does a pretty good job of defining this for us:

Prospect theory is a theory in cognitive psychology that describes the way people choose between probabilistic alternatives that involve risk, where the probabilities of outcomes are uncertain. The theory states that people make decisions based on the potential value of losses and gains rather than the final outcome, and that people evaluate these losses and gains using some heuristics. The model is descriptive: it tries to model real-life choices, rather than optimal decisions, as normative models do. The theory was created in 1979 and developed in 1992 by Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky as a psychologically more accurate description of decision making, compared to the expected utility theory. In the original formulation, the term prospect referred to a lottery. The paper “Prospect Theory: An Analysis of Decision under Risk” (1979) has been called a “seminal paper in behavioral economics”.

–source: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prospect_theory

Prospect theory is really about how we as individuals and as a group of human beings evaluate potential losses and potential gains. Is a gain considered just as desirable as avoiding a loss? If not, how do we emotionally weight gains compared to losses? Do we work harder to avoid losses than to seek gains?

Prospect theory is not a simplistic answer to these questions, but a general theory that seeks to explain how humans answer them. To make matters more complicated, the groundbreaking work on prospect theory by Daniel Kahneman–who won a Nobel Prize in Economics for his work—has not always replicated by subsequent studies (https://www.apa.org/science/about/psa/2015/01/gains-losses.aspx). All this to say this area of inquiry into how humans handle risk is imperfect and still developing, but prospect theory is still a useful tool that’s more sophisticated than simply asking “how do you respond to risk?”

5) Your DiSC work personality profile. David C. Baker has done some really great research into the relationship between entrepreneurial risk-taking and the 4 work personality characteristics the DiSC profile seeks to quantify. That’s why I’ve started using this tool as part of my risk assessment work with clients. It casts a useful, nuanced light on the same issue the questions above are getting at, but from the perspective of personality rather than past behavior or risk/reward preferences.

Taken together, these five factors give a good picture of your risk profile which again is a combination of your emotional comfort with risk and your ability to withstand a financial loss.

At the end of this chapter I’ll share a simplified tool you can self-administer to assess your own risk profile.

11.4 Head Start vs. Find Your People/Opportunity vs. Entrepreneurial Thesis

To complete your understanding of how risk fits into specializing, we need to dig into one more big idea, which we might think of as three different decision making heuristics. These are patterns I’ve noticed among the specialists I’ve interviewed for my podcast, and they form three different ways of answering the question: “how do I decide where to specialize?”. These three decision making heuristics each present a different risk/reward tradeoff, so we’ll move through them in order from lowest to highest risk.

Note: Chapter 12 will bring these three heuristics together into a single process you can self-administer, so as you’re reading through these heuristics there’s no need to try to implement them until you get to Chapter 12.

Another note: These heuristics will portray 3 different decisions making styles, and it may seem that you should fit neatly and cleanly into only one of those 3 buckets. The reality is almost always more nuanced, and you may find yourself combining two of these approaches. That’s totally normal, but I’ll talk about them as if they are 3 things with distinct borders between them, even though they’re really not.

11.4.1 Find Your Head Start

When you find your head start, instead of looking equally at all the factors that might make for a good specialization, you focus on one: where is your most significant head start?

{TODO: remind folks what constitutes a head start, possible pull from ch10}

You don’t ignore those other factors. Here’s what you actually do instead:

List every way of specializing that might be a fit for your business.
Rank each of those ways of specializing based on how much of a head start you have there, and how beneficial that head start would be.
Use other factors to eliminate options from your list. Other factors might include:

The risk of specializing in this way
The low profitability of working with clients like those
A lack of interest on your part in doing work like this
Low demand from clients for this specialized offering
How deep your insight into the problem or the needs of the vertical goes

At this point you have a shortlist of specialization options. They’re all free from dealbreaker flaws, and they’re ranked based on how beneficial your head start in each one is.

Now, if your shortlist is longer than 1 item, you still have a decision to make, but this simple decision making heuristic has hopefully supplied you with a shortlist of manageable size.

11.4.2 Find Your People/Opportunity

The next decision making heuristic is to ignore your head start and instead focus on a different single factor: what kind of clients do you prefer to serve, or what problems do you find most fascinating and compelling?

Again, you’re not ignoring other factors, you’re just using a two-pass rank-and-eliminate heuristic, where the first pass is to compile a list of interests. This time, it goes like this:

Make a list of kinds of clients you are confident you would enjoy working with. Big fat important note: you are not allowed to list stuff like “pays invoices on time”, “innovative”, or “lets me lead”. These are not ways of identifying clients that lead you to a useful specialization decision. Of course we all want to work with great clients and avoid bad ones, but remember specialization is a way to make your marketing work better and set you up to cultivate very valuable expertise, and having a focus on “clients that pay invoices on time” does neither of those.
Your list does not need to be limited to types of clients you have worked with in the past. That’s why I call this heuristic Find Your People/Opportunity, because it’s based on the idea that you’ll volunteer to take on more risk so that you can seek out types of clients you may not have worked with before but for some reason really would like to. It’s risky to do this, but if you can handle the risk it can be a way to improve your career.
Rank your list by how much you would like to work with each kind of client you have listed.
Then, as in the Find Your Head Start heuristic, eliminate options from your list based on other important factors. As you do this, remember that this list is, by its nature, a list of potentially risky ways for you to specialize. You really do need to have a combination of 1) a risk profile that allows you to handle a fair bit of risk, 2) patience, 3) discipline, and 4) a burning desire to do the work necessary to build a market position without having a head start that gets you closer to that market position. Reasons to eliminate options might include:

An insurmountable lack of access to buyers in this area of focus
No conceivable overlap between what this market values and what you are willing to offer

This approach to deciding how to specialize is more risky. This is a good place to remind you that for all the power, reach, and flexibility that modern digital marketing gives us for generating leads, and for all the power that Google and LinkedIn give buyers for finding solutions they may not have been aware of before they searched, you’re still in a relationship business. Your ability to forge trusting relationships with buyers is the beating heart of your ability to run a thriving consulting business. This doesn’t mean you need to be an extrovert or have world-class people skills. Lots of nerdy introverts, like myself, do it. So the risk this heuristic poses to you is that you could choose to specialize in a way where it’s difficult or impractical for you to forge trusting relationships with enough buyers to make it work.

If you’re using the Find Your Head Start heuristic, you’re probably going to specialize in a vertical or problem you have past experience with. You’ll know what to expect. You may already have a useful amount of access to buyers or credibility. With the Find Your People/Opportunity heuristic, you may be moving into unfamiliar territory with surprises in store for you. The solution, of course, is to do some market research to make the new territory less unfamiliar.

This is also a good place to remind you that I see the kind of people who read a book like this as way above average in terms of creativity, resourcefulness, and willingness to learn and change. My clients are all like this, and it’s a never-ending joy to work with people with this kind of drive and growth mindset. So if you have a fire in your belly to Find Your People/Opportunity and the risk profile to handle it, I believe you can build the access and trust you need, perhaps in less time than it takes to get a masters degree.

11.4.3 Entrepreneurial Thesis

The final decision making heuristic I’ve seen out in the wild is what I call the Entrepreneurial Thesis. This is actually a variation of the Find Your People/Opportunity approach, but it’s better suited to someone who is more mercenary or entrepreneurial in their overall orientation to risk & opportunity. This mercenary or entrepreneurial orientation is often correlated with a reduced need for craftsman-like enjoyment of the work. Or rather, the craftsmanship shows up in the design of the business rather than the creation of deliverables.

Instead of looking for what kind of clients you prefer to serve, or what problems you find most fascinating and compelling, you are looking for the opportunity that seems like the best bridge from your current position to a significant entrepreneurial opportunity.

I’ve interviewed several business owners who deployed this decision making heuristic when they decided how to specialize. They speak about interest and enjoyment in distinctly different ways than people who gravitate towards the other two decision making heuristics. Here are some verbatim quotes that illustrate this point:

TODO: look up the Elliot interview

TODO: look up the Matt Rogish interview

Notice how Elliot and Matt both talk about the opportunity they chose to focus on in terms of its business potential first. In fact, Elliot goes so far to compare the opportunity he pursued to janitorial work. Dirty, smelly, and mundane. That’s how most of us would think of janitorial work, and it’s exactly those repellant characteristics that attracted Elliot to this opportunity! He saw the inherent un-sexyness of the work as a “moat” that would deter most competition, and one that would also tend to keep his clients from adding this expertise in-house and therefore ensure long-term demand for an outsourced solution that Elliot could provide.

So the Entrepreneurial Thesis heuristic is more like the Find Your Head Start heuristic and much less like the Find Your People/Opportunity heuristic in that the potential business upside of the opportunity is the most important factor in how you decide to specialize, and factors like enjoyment of the people or enjoyment of the work are much less important.

In fact, you may have a head start that you can leverage into an entrepreneurial endeavor. Matt Rogish is a good example of this. His strongest head start was in DevOps work, and the cost and pain of migrating away from Heroku created the opportunity for him to build a team that could pursue that opportunity. Does he dislike DevOps work? Not at all. But every aspect of how he pursued the opportunity he saw to deliver DevOps as a service was done in an entrepreneurial, decouple-time-from-revenue way.

There’s one more subtle distinction I want to talk about here, because it’s especially relevant when pursuing an Entrepreneurial Thesis.

It has to do with the idea of putting your market first.

As n00b freelancers, lots of us do the opposite of a market-first approach to our businesses. We start with some skills that we probably developed while working a job, and we launch into self-employment with this skillset as our focus. We define ourselves or our value proposition based on this skillset.

Eventually, some of us arrive at the market-first orientation after the frustration with the ceiling that a skills-first orientation puts on our career. We start to wonder if we could generate more revenue or create more impact with a different approach.

The answer is yes. And the different approach is a market-first approach.

A market-first approach starts with a focus on a market, either defined vertically or horizontally. We focus on that market, and then do whatever we can to literally fall in love with it. There’s really no better term for developing the empathy and the intimacy with the market. This love affair leads you to put the needs of the market first, and as you better and better understand those needs, you better understand where there might be value in addressing certain of those needs. This deeper understanding of what the market needs and values leads you to re-focus or even re-invent your services in a way that targets the more valuable needs the market has.

Taking this approach all the way may lead you to an Entrepreneurial Thesis. I have a coaching client doing just that with a need that she and a few other see around the problem of software contributing to physician burnout. What makes this an Entrepreneurial Thesis is that there’s no competition that validates that others can make this kind of focus work. She’s a pioneer. Things can work out very well for smart pioneers. Among their ranks are companies like AirBnB and Uber and other “unicorns”. But it is risky! Taking a market-first approach is the best way to de-risk an Entrepreneurial Thesis. The other approach of dreaming up an idea, skipping a thorough a half-assed validation phase, and moving straight to execution is a surefire recipe for failure. Much better to let your market generate ideas for you.

Again, I’ve listed these three decision making heuristics in order from lowest to highest risk. In Chapter 12 I’ll bring these concepts of risk profile and decision making style together into a simple process you can follow to get closer to deciding how your business could specialize and get started building a great market position. So that means we need to do one more thing in this chapter, which is get a handle on your risk profile.

11.5 Risk Self-Assessment

TODO: build a version of my current risk assessment that doesn’t include the DiSC profile and automate it so that it calculates risk score and sends that back to folks who take it, and link book readers to that version.

11.6 Chapter Summary

Chapter 2 Who This Manual is For

I sincerely hope this manual is extremely useful to you as you attempt to solve one of the most common problems in individually owned technical services firms: the lack of proper positioning. If at any point in working your way through this manual you run across problems, I encourage you to contact me directly. I’m Philip Morgan, and I help custom software development shops get more leads without hiring a sales person. I use positioning, education-based content marketing, and marketing automation to make that happen. You can reach me via email at philip@philipmorganconsulting.com.

2.1 Who This Manual is For

This manual will be most helpful to a narrow range of people:

Owners of technical services firms like programming consultancies, web or digital agencies, and SaaS companies.
Independent consultants or freelancers of many stripes, though all my examples in this manual are specific to the technical rather than the creative end of the professional services spectrum.
People who are considering making the leap to solo self-employment but haven’t done it yet.
Self-employed people who need to be making more money within 12 months, but can invest 6 months of effort to lay the foundation.

This manual will not be immediately helpful to you if you have very limited work experience or “the wolf is at the door” in terms of your finances. Developing a desirable market position requires discipline in client selection and negotiation that will be very difficult to muster if you have little savings, credit, or leeway in terms of saying no to work in the short term. Making a good positioning choice requires a certain amount of self-awareness about your strengths and preferences, and you just can’t discover that stuff without a year or two of full-time client work under your belt.

Finally, this manual is meant to be concise. How many 80,000-word business books have you read that should have been 20,000 words? So many business books are one meaningful but straightforward insight padded out with redundant content to make a publisher happy. This one is not.

Even with a few interruptions you should be able to read this book cover to cover in 2 hours or less. I’m confident you’ll get a world class ROI on that modest time investment.